<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<chapter id="chapter8-en">

<head2 id="en00480">CHAPTER VIII.</head2>

<head3 id="en00481">The Queen&rsquo;s Croquet-Ground</head3>

<para id="en00482">
A large rose-tree stood near the entrance of the garden: the roses growing on
it were white, but there were three gardeners at it, busily painting them red.
Alice thought this a very curious thing, and she went nearer to watch them, and
just as she came up to them she heard one of them say, &ldquo;Look out now,
Five! Don&rsquo;t go splashing paint over me like that!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00483">
&ldquo;I couldn&rsquo;t help it,&rdquo; said Five, in a sulky tone;
&ldquo;Seven jogged my elbow.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00484">
On which Seven looked up and said, &ldquo;That&rsquo;s right, Five! Always lay
the blame on others!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00485">
&ldquo;&lt;i&gt;You&rsquo;d&lt;/i&gt; better not talk!&rdquo; said Five. &ldquo;I heard the
Queen say only yesterday you deserved to be beheaded!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00486">
&ldquo;What for?&rdquo; said the one who had spoken first.</para>

<para id="en00487">
&ldquo;That&rsquo;s none of &lt;i&gt;your&lt;/i&gt; business, Two!&rdquo; said Seven.</para>

<para id="en00488">
&ldquo;Yes, it &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; his business!&rdquo; said Five, &ldquo;and I&rsquo;ll
tell him&mdash;it was for bringing the cook tulip-roots instead of
onions.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00489">
Seven flung down his brush, and had just begun &ldquo;Well, of all the unjust
things&mdash;&rdquo; when his eye chanced to fall upon Alice, as she stood
watching them, and he checked himself suddenly: the others looked round also,
and all of them bowed low.</para>

<para id="en00490">
&ldquo;Would you tell me,&rdquo; said Alice, a little timidly, &ldquo;why you
are painting those roses?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00491">
Five and Seven said nothing, but looked at Two. Two began in a low voice,
&ldquo;Why the fact is, you see, Miss, this here ought to have been a
&lt;i&gt;red&lt;/i&gt; rose-tree, and we put a white one in by mistake; and if the Queen
was to find it out, we should all have our heads cut off, you know. So you see,
Miss, we&rsquo;re doing our best, afore she comes, to&mdash;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00492">
At this moment Five, who had been anxiously looking across the garden, called out
&ldquo;The Queen! The Queen!&rdquo; and the three gardeners instantly threw
themselves flat upon their faces. There was a sound of many footsteps, and
Alice looked round, eager to see the Queen.</para>

<para id="en00493">
First came ten soldiers carrying clubs; these were all shaped like the three
gardeners, oblong and flat, with their hands and feet at the corners: next the
ten courtiers; these were ornamented all over with diamonds, and walked two and
two, as the soldiers did. After these came the royal children; there were ten
of them, and the little dears came jumping merrily along hand in hand, in
couples: they were all ornamented with hearts. Next came the guests, mostly
Kings and Queens, and among them Alice recognised the White Rabbit: it was
talking in a hurried nervous manner, smiling at everything that was said, and
went by without noticing her. Then followed the Knave of Hearts, carrying the
King&rsquo;s crown on a crimson velvet cushion; and, last of all this grand
procession, came THE KING AND QUEEN OF HEARTS.</para>

<para id="en00494">
Alice was rather doubtful whether she ought not to lie down on her face like
the three gardeners, but she could not remember ever having heard of such a
rule at processions; &ldquo;and besides, what would be the use of a
procession,&rdquo; thought she, &ldquo;if people had all to lie down upon their
faces, so that they couldn&rsquo;t see it?&rdquo; So she stood still where she
was, and waited.</para>

<para id="en00495">
When the procession came opposite to Alice, they all stopped and looked at her,
and the Queen said severely &ldquo;Who is this?&rdquo; She said it to the Knave
of Hearts, who only bowed and smiled in reply.</para>

<para id="en00496">
&ldquo;Idiot!&rdquo; said the Queen, tossing her head impatiently; and, turning
to Alice, she went on, &ldquo;What&rsquo;s your name, child?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00497">
&ldquo;My name is Alice, so please your Majesty,&rdquo; said Alice very
politely; but she added, to herself, &ldquo;Why, they&rsquo;re only a pack of
cards, after all. I needn&rsquo;t be afraid of them!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00498">
&ldquo;And who are &lt;i&gt;these?&lt;/i&gt;&rdquo; said the Queen, pointing to the three
gardeners who were lying round the rose-tree; for, you see, as they were lying
on their faces, and the pattern on their backs was the same as the rest of the
pack, she could not tell whether they were gardeners, or soldiers, or
courtiers, or three of her own children.</para>

<para id="en00499">
&ldquo;How should &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; know?&rdquo; said Alice, surprised at her own
courage. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s no business of &lt;i&gt;mine&lt;/i&gt;.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00500">
The Queen turned crimson with fury, and, after glaring at her for a moment like
a wild beast, screamed &ldquo;Off with her head! Off&mdash;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00501">
&ldquo;Nonsense!&rdquo; said Alice, very loudly and decidedly, and the Queen
was silent.</para>

<para id="en00502">
The King laid his hand upon her arm, and timidly said &ldquo;Consider, my dear:
she is only a child!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00503">
The Queen turned angrily away from him, and said to the Knave &ldquo;Turn them
over!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00504">
The Knave did so, very carefully, with one foot.</para>

<para id="en00505">
&ldquo;Get up!&rdquo; said the Queen, in a shrill, loud voice, and the three
gardeners instantly jumped up, and began bowing to the King, the Queen, the
royal children, and everybody else.</para>

<para id="en00506">
&ldquo;Leave off that!&rdquo; screamed the Queen. &ldquo;You make me
giddy.&rdquo; And then, turning to the rose-tree, she went on, &ldquo;What
&lt;i&gt;have&lt;/i&gt; you been doing here?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00507">
&ldquo;May it please your Majesty,&rdquo; said Two, in a very humble tone,
going down on one knee as he spoke, &ldquo;we were trying&mdash;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00508">
&ldquo;&lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; see!&rdquo; said the Queen, who had meanwhile been examining
the roses. &ldquo;Off with their heads!&rdquo; and the procession moved on,
three of the soldiers remaining behind to execute the unfortunate gardeners,
who ran to Alice for protection.</para>

<para id="en00509">
&ldquo;You shan&rsquo;t be beheaded!&rdquo; said Alice, and she put them into a
large flower-pot that stood near. The three soldiers wandered about for a
minute or two, looking for them, and then quietly marched off after the others.</para>

<para id="en00510">
&ldquo;Are their heads off?&rdquo; shouted the Queen.</para>

<para id="en00511">
&ldquo;Their heads are gone, if it please your Majesty!&rdquo; the soldiers
shouted in reply.</para>

<para id="en00512">
&ldquo;That&rsquo;s right!&rdquo; shouted the Queen. &ldquo;Can you play
croquet?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00513">
The soldiers were silent, and looked at Alice, as the question was evidently
meant for her.</para>

<para id="en00514">
&ldquo;Yes!&rdquo; shouted Alice.</para>

<para id="en00515">
&ldquo;Come on, then!&rdquo; roared the Queen, and Alice joined the procession,
wondering very much what would happen next.</para>

<para id="en00516">
&ldquo;It&rsquo;s&mdash;it&rsquo;s a very fine day!&rdquo; said a timid voice
at her side. She was walking by the White Rabbit, who was peeping anxiously
into her face.</para>

<para id="en00517">
&ldquo;Very,&rdquo; said Alice: &ldquo;&mdash;where&rsquo;s the Duchess?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00518">
&ldquo;Hush! Hush!&rdquo; said the Rabbit in a low, hurried tone. He looked
anxiously over his shoulder as he spoke, and then raised himself upon tiptoe,
put his mouth close to her ear, and whispered &ldquo;She&rsquo;s under sentence
of execution.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00519">
&ldquo;What for?&rdquo; said Alice.</para>

<para id="en00520">
&ldquo;Did you say &lsquo;What a pity!&rsquo;?&rdquo; the Rabbit asked.</para>

<para id="en00521">
&ldquo;No, I didn&rsquo;t,&rdquo; said Alice: &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t think
it&rsquo;s at all a pity. I said &lsquo;What for?&rsquo;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00522">
&ldquo;She boxed the Queen&rsquo;s ears&mdash;&rdquo; the Rabbit began. Alice
gave a little scream of laughter. &ldquo;Oh, hush!&rdquo; the Rabbit whispered
in a frightened tone. &ldquo;The Queen will hear you! You see, she came rather
late, and the Queen said&mdash;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00523">
&ldquo;Get to your places!&rdquo; shouted the Queen in a voice of thunder, and
people began running about in all directions, tumbling up against each other;
however, they got settled down in a minute or two, and the game began.</para>

<para id="en00524">
Alice thought she had never seen such a curious croquet-ground in her life;
it was all ridges and furrows; the balls were live hedgehogs, the mallets live
flamingoes, and the soldiers had to double themselves up and to stand on their
hands and feet, to make the arches.</para>

<para id="en00525">
The chief difficulty Alice found at first was in managing her flamingo: she
succeeded in getting its body tucked away, comfortably enough, under her arm,
with its legs hanging down, but generally, just as she had got its neck nicely
straightened out, and was going to give the hedgehog a blow with its head, it
&lt;i&gt;would&lt;/i&gt; twist itself round and look up in her face, with such a puzzled
expression that she could not help bursting out laughing: and when she had got
its head down, and was going to begin again, it was very provoking to find that
the hedgehog had unrolled itself, and was in the act of crawling away: besides
all this, there was generally a ridge or furrow in the way wherever she wanted
to send the hedgehog to, and, as the doubled-up soldiers were always getting up
and walking off to other parts of the ground, Alice soon came to the conclusion
that it was a very difficult game indeed.</para>

<para id="en00526">
The players all played at once without waiting for turns, quarrelling all the
while, and fighting for the hedgehogs; and in a very short time the Queen was
in a furious passion, and went stamping about, and shouting &ldquo;Off with his
head!&rdquo; or &ldquo;Off with her head!&rdquo; about once in a minute.</para>

<para id="en00527">
Alice began to feel very uneasy: to be sure, she had not as yet had any dispute
with the Queen, but she knew that it might happen any minute, &ldquo;and
then,&rdquo; thought she, &ldquo;what would become of me? They&rsquo;re
dreadfully fond of beheading people here; the great wonder is, that
there&rsquo;s any one left alive!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00528">
She was looking about for some way of escape, and wondering whether she could
get away without being seen, when she noticed a curious appearance in the air:
it puzzled her very much at first, but, after watching it a minute or two, she
made it out to be a grin, and she said to herself &ldquo;It&rsquo;s the
Cheshire Cat: now I shall have somebody to talk to.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00529">
&ldquo;How are you getting on?&rdquo; said the Cat, as soon as there was mouth
enough for it to speak with.</para>

<para id="en00530">
Alice waited till the eyes appeared, and then nodded. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s no use
speaking to it,&rdquo; she thought, &ldquo;till its ears have come, or at least
one of them.&rdquo; In another minute the whole head appeared, and then Alice
put down her flamingo, and began an account of the game, feeling very glad she
had someone to listen to her. The Cat seemed to think that there was enough of
it now in sight, and no more of it appeared.</para>

<para id="en00531">
&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t think they play at all fairly,&rdquo; Alice began, in
rather a complaining tone, &ldquo;and they all quarrel so dreadfully one
can&rsquo;t hear oneself speak&mdash;and they don&rsquo;t seem to have any
rules in particular; at least, if there are, nobody attends to them&mdash;and
you&rsquo;ve no idea how confusing it is all the things being alive; for
instance, there&rsquo;s the arch I&rsquo;ve got to go through next walking
about at the other end of the ground&mdash;and I should have croqueted the
Queen&rsquo;s hedgehog just now, only it ran away when it saw mine
coming!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00532">
&ldquo;How do you like the Queen?&rdquo; said the Cat in a low voice.</para>

<para id="en00533">
&ldquo;Not at all,&rdquo; said Alice: &ldquo;she&rsquo;s so
extremely&mdash;&rdquo; Just then she noticed that the Queen was close behind
her, listening: so she went on, &ldquo;&mdash;likely to win, that it&rsquo;s
hardly worth while finishing the game.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00534">
The Queen smiled and passed on.</para>

<para id="en00535">
&ldquo;Who &lt;i&gt;are&lt;/i&gt; you talking to?&rdquo; said the King, going up
to Alice, and looking at the Cat&rsquo;s head with great curiosity.</para>

<para id="en00536">
&ldquo;It&rsquo;s a friend of mine&mdash;a Cheshire Cat,&rdquo; said Alice:
&ldquo;allow me to introduce it.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00537">
&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t like the look of it at all,&rdquo; said the King:
&ldquo;however, it may kiss my hand if it likes.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00538">
&ldquo;I&rsquo;d rather not,&rdquo; the Cat remarked.</para>

<para id="en00539">
&ldquo;Don&rsquo;t be impertinent,&rdquo; said the King, &ldquo;and don&rsquo;t
look at me like that!&rdquo; He got behind Alice as he spoke.</para>

<para id="en00540">
&ldquo;A cat may look at a king,&rdquo; said Alice. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve read that
in some book, but I don&rsquo;t remember where.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00541">
&ldquo;Well, it must be removed,&rdquo; said the King very decidedly, and he
called the Queen, who was passing at the moment, &ldquo;My dear! I wish you
would have this cat removed!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00542">
The Queen had only one way of settling all difficulties, great or small.
&ldquo;Off with his head!&rdquo; she said, without even looking round.</para>

<para id="en00543">
&ldquo;I&rsquo;ll fetch the executioner myself,&rdquo; said the King eagerly,
and he hurried off.</para>

<para id="en00544">
Alice thought she might as well go back, and see how the game was going on, as
she heard the Queen&rsquo;s voice in the distance, screaming with passion. She
had already heard her sentence three of the players to be executed for having
missed their turns, and she did not like the look of things at all, as the game
was in such confusion that she never knew whether it was her turn or not. So
she went in search of her hedgehog.</para>

<para id="en00545">
The hedgehog was engaged in a fight with another hedgehog, which seemed to
Alice an excellent opportunity for croqueting one of them with the other: the
only difficulty was, that her flamingo was gone across to the other side of the
garden, where Alice could see it trying in a helpless sort of way to fly up
into a tree.</para>

<para id="en00546">
By the time she had caught the flamingo and brought it back, the fight was
over, and both the hedgehogs were out of sight: &ldquo;but it doesn&rsquo;t
matter much,&rdquo; thought Alice, &ldquo;as all the arches are gone from this
side of the ground.&rdquo; So she tucked it away under her arm, that it might
not escape again, and went back for a little more conversation with her friend.</para>

<para id="en00547">
When she got back to the Cheshire Cat, she was surprised to find quite a large
crowd collected round it: there was a dispute going on between the executioner,
the King, and the Queen, who were all talking at once, while all the rest were
quite silent, and looked very uncomfortable.</para>

<para id="en00548">
The moment Alice appeared, she was appealed to by all three to settle the
question, and they repeated their arguments to her, though, as they all spoke
at once, she found it very hard indeed to make out exactly what they said.</para>

<para id="en00549">
The executioner&rsquo;s argument was, that you couldn&rsquo;t cut off a head
unless there was a body to cut it off from: that he had never had to do such a
thing before, and he wasn&rsquo;t going to begin at &lt;i&gt;his&lt;/i&gt; time
of life.</para>

<para id="en00550">
The King&rsquo;s argument was, that anything that had a head could be beheaded,
and that you weren&rsquo;t to talk nonsense.</para>

<para id="en00551">
The Queen&rsquo;s argument was, that if something wasn&rsquo;t done about it in
less than no time she&rsquo;d have everybody executed, all round. (It was this
last remark that had made the whole party look so grave and anxious.)</para>

<para id="en00552">
Alice could think of nothing else to say but &ldquo;It belongs to the Duchess:
you&rsquo;d better ask &lt;i&gt;her&lt;/i&gt; about it.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00553">
&ldquo;She&rsquo;s in prison,&rdquo; the Queen said to the executioner:
&ldquo;fetch her here.&rdquo; And the executioner went off like an arrow.</para>

<para id="en00554">
The Cat&rsquo;s head began fading away the moment he was gone, and, by the time
he had come back with the Duchess, it had entirely disappeared; so the King and
the executioner ran wildly up and down looking for it, while the rest of the
party went back to the game.</para>

</chapter>
