<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<chapter id="chapter3-en">

<head2 id="en00080">CHAPTER III.</head2>

<head3 id="en00081">A Caucus-Race and a Long Tale</head3>

<para id="en00082">
They were indeed a queer-looking party that assembled on the bank&mdash;the
birds with draggled feathers, the animals with their fur clinging close to
them, and all dripping wet, cross, and uncomfortable.</para>

<para id="en00083">
The first question of course was, how to get dry again: they had a consultation
about this, and after a few minutes it seemed quite natural to Alice to find
herself talking familiarly with them, as if she had known them all her life.
Indeed, she had quite a long argument with the Lory, who at last turned sulky,
and would only say, &ldquo;I am older than you, and must know better;&rdquo;
and this Alice would not allow without knowing how old it was, and, as the Lory
positively refused to tell its age, there was no more to be said.</para>

<para id="en00084">
At last the Mouse, who seemed to be a person of authority among them, called
out, &ldquo;Sit down, all of you, and listen to me! &lt;i&gt;I&rsquo;ll&lt;/i&gt;
soon make you dry enough!&rdquo; They all sat down at once, in a large ring, with
the Mouse in the middle. Alice kept her eyes anxiously fixed on it, for she felt
sure she would catch a bad cold if she did not get dry very soon.</para>

<para id="en00085">
&ldquo;Ahem!&rdquo; said the Mouse with an important air, &ldquo;are you all
ready? This is the driest thing I know. Silence all round, if you please!
&lsquo;William the Conqueror, whose cause was favoured by the pope, was soon
submitted to by the English, who wanted leaders, and had been of late much
accustomed to usurpation and conquest. Edwin and Morcar, the earls of Mercia
and Northumbria&mdash;&rsquo;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00086">
&ldquo;Ugh!&rdquo; said the Lory, with a shiver.</para>

<para id="en00087">
&ldquo;I beg your pardon!&rdquo; said the Mouse, frowning, but very politely:
&ldquo;Did you speak?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00088">
&ldquo;Not I!&rdquo; said the Lory hastily.</para>

<para id="en00089">
&ldquo;I thought you did,&rdquo; said the Mouse. &ldquo;&mdash;I proceed.
&lsquo;Edwin and Morcar, the earls of Mercia and Northumbria, declared for him:
and even Stigand, the patriotic archbishop of Canterbury, found it
advisable&mdash;&rsquo;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00090">
&ldquo;Found &lt;i&gt;what&lt;/i&gt;?&rdquo; said the Duck.</para>

<para id="en00091">
&ldquo;Found &lt;i&gt;it&lt;/i&gt;,&rdquo; the Mouse replied rather crossly: &ldquo;of
course you know what &lsquo;it&rsquo; means.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00092">
&ldquo;I know what &lsquo;it&rsquo; means well enough, when &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; find a
thing,&rdquo; said the Duck: &ldquo;it&rsquo;s generally a frog or a worm. The
question is, what did the archbishop find?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00093">
The Mouse did not notice this question, but hurriedly went on,
&ldquo;&lsquo;&mdash;found it advisable to go with Edgar Atheling to meet
William and offer him the crown. William&rsquo;s conduct at first was moderate.
But the insolence of his Normans&mdash;&rsquo; How are you getting on now, my
dear?&rdquo; it continued, turning to Alice as it spoke.</para>

<para id="en00094">
&ldquo;As wet as ever,&rdquo; said Alice in a melancholy tone: &ldquo;it
doesn&rsquo;t seem to dry me at all.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00095">
&ldquo;In that case,&rdquo; said the Dodo solemnly, rising to its feet,
&ldquo;I move that the meeting adjourn, for the immediate adoption of more
energetic remedies&mdash;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00096">
&ldquo;Speak English!&rdquo; said the Eaglet. &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t know the
meaning of half those long words, and, what&rsquo;s more, I don&rsquo;t believe
you do either!&rdquo; And the Eaglet bent down its head to hide a smile: some
of the other birds tittered audibly.</para>

<para id="en00097">
&ldquo;What I was going to say,&rdquo; said the Dodo in an offended tone,
&ldquo;was, that the best thing to get us dry would be a Caucus-race.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00098">
&ldquo;What &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a Caucus-race?&rdquo; said Alice; not that she wanted
much to know, but the Dodo had paused as if it thought that &lt;i&gt;somebody&lt;/i&gt;
ought to speak, and no one else seemed inclined to say anything.</para>

<para id="en00099">
&ldquo;Why,&rdquo; said the Dodo, &ldquo;the best way to explain it is to do
it.&rdquo; (And, as you might like to try the thing yourself, some winter day,
I will tell you how the Dodo managed it.)</para>

<para id="en00100">
First it marked out a race-course, in a sort of circle, (&ldquo;the exact shape
doesn&rsquo;t matter,&rdquo; it said,) and then all the party were placed along
the course, here and there. There was no &ldquo;One, two, three, and
away,&rdquo; but they began running when they liked, and left off when they
liked, so that it was not easy to know when the race was over. However, when
they had been running half an hour or so, and were quite dry again, the Dodo
suddenly called out &ldquo;The race is over!&rdquo; and they all crowded round
it, panting, and asking, &ldquo;But who has won?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00101">
This question the Dodo could not answer without a great deal of thought, and it
sat for a long time with one finger pressed upon its forehead (the position in
which you usually see Shakespeare, in the pictures of him), while the rest
waited in silence. At last the Dodo said, &ldquo;&lt;i&gt;Everybody&lt;/i&gt; has won,
and all must have prizes.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00102">
&ldquo;But who is to give the prizes?&rdquo; quite a chorus of voices asked.</para>

<para id="en00103">
&ldquo;Why, &lt;i&gt;she&lt;/i&gt;, of course,&rdquo; said the Dodo, pointing to Alice
with one finger; and the whole party at once crowded round her, calling out in a
confused way, &ldquo;Prizes! Prizes!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00104">
Alice had no idea what to do, and in despair she put her hand in her pocket,
and pulled out a box of comfits, (luckily the salt water had not got into it),
and handed them round as prizes. There was exactly one a-piece, all round.</para>

<para id="en00105">
&ldquo;But she must have a prize herself, you know,&rdquo; said the Mouse.</para>

<para id="en00106">
&ldquo;Of course,&rdquo; the Dodo replied very gravely. &ldquo;What else have
you got in your pocket?&rdquo; he went on, turning to Alice.</para>

<para id="en00107">
&ldquo;Only a thimble,&rdquo; said Alice sadly.</para>

<para id="en00108">
&ldquo;Hand it over here,&rdquo; said the Dodo.
&lt;br/&gt;
Then they all crowded round her once more, while the Dodo solemnly presented
the thimble, saying &ldquo;We beg your acceptance of this elegant
thimble;&rdquo; and, when it had finished this short speech, they all cheered.</para>

<para id="en00109">
Alice thought the whole thing very absurd, but they all looked so grave that
she did not dare to laugh; and, as she could not think of anything to say, she
simply bowed, and took the thimble, looking as solemn as she could.</para>

<para id="en00110">
The next thing was to eat the comfits: this caused some noise and confusion, as
the large birds complained that they could not taste theirs, and the small ones
choked and had to be patted on the back. However, it was over at last, and they
sat down again in a ring, and begged the Mouse to tell them something more.</para>

<para id="en00111">
&ldquo;You promised to tell me your history, you know,&rdquo; said Alice,
&ldquo;and why it is you hate&mdash;C and D,&rdquo; she added in a whisper,
half afraid that it would be offended again.</para>

<para id="en00112">
&ldquo;Mine is a long and a sad tale!&rdquo; said the Mouse, turning to Alice,
and sighing.</para>

<para id="en00113">
&ldquo;It &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a long tail, certainly,&rdquo; said Alice, looking down
with wonder at the Mouse&rsquo;s tail; &ldquo;but why do you call it
sad?&rdquo; And she kept on puzzling about it while the Mouse was speaking, so
that her idea of the tale was something like this:&mdash;</para>

<para id="en00114">
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;Fury said to a&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; mouse, That he&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;met in the&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; house,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &lsquo;Let us&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;both go to&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; law: &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; will&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;prosecute&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt;.&mdash;Come,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; I&rsquo;ll take no&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; denial; We&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;must have a&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;trial: For&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;really this&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; morning I&rsquo;ve&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp;nothing&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp;to do.&rsquo;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Said the&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;mouse to the&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; cur, &lsquo;Such&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;a trial,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; dear sir,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;With&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;no jury&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;or judge,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; would be&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;wasting&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;our&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;breath.&rsquo;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&lsquo;I&rsquo;ll be&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;judge, I&rsquo;ll&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; be jury,&rsquo;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Said&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; cunning&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;old Fury:&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&lsquo;I&rsquo;ll&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;try the&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;whole&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;cause,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;and&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; condemn&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; you&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;to&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; death.&rsquo;&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
</para>

<para id="en00115">
&ldquo;You are not attending!&rdquo; said the Mouse to Alice severely.
&ldquo;What are you thinking of?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00116">
&ldquo;I beg your pardon,&rdquo; said Alice very humbly: &ldquo;you had got to
the fifth bend, I think?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00117">
&ldquo;I had &lt;i&gt;not!&lt;/i&gt;&rdquo; cried the Mouse, sharply and very
angrily.</para>

<para id="en00118">
&ldquo;A knot!&rdquo; said Alice, always ready to make herself useful, and
looking anxiously about her. &ldquo;Oh, do let me help to undo it!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00119">
&ldquo;I shall do nothing of the sort,&rdquo; said the Mouse, getting up and
walking away. &ldquo;You insult me by talking such nonsense!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00120">
&ldquo;I didn&rsquo;t mean it!&rdquo; pleaded poor Alice. &ldquo;But
you&rsquo;re so easily offended, you know!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00121">
The Mouse only growled in reply.</para>

<para id="en00122">
&ldquo;Please come back and finish your story!&rdquo; Alice called after it;
and the others all joined in chorus, &ldquo;Yes, please do!&rdquo; but the
Mouse only shook its head impatiently, and walked a little quicker.</para>

<para id="en00123">
&ldquo;What a pity it wouldn&rsquo;t stay!&rdquo; sighed the Lory, as soon as
it was quite out of sight; and an old Crab took the opportunity of saying to
her daughter &ldquo;Ah, my dear! Let this be a lesson to you never to lose
&lt;i&gt;your&lt;/i&gt; temper!&rdquo; &ldquo;Hold your tongue, Ma!&rdquo; said
the young Crab, a little snappishly. &ldquo;You&rsquo;re enough to try the patience
of an oyster!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00124">
&ldquo;I wish I had our Dinah here, I know I do!&rdquo; said Alice aloud,
addressing nobody in particular. &ldquo;She&rsquo;d soon fetch it back!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00125">
&ldquo;And who is Dinah, if I might venture to ask the question?&rdquo; said
the Lory.</para>

<para id="en00126">
Alice replied eagerly, for she was always ready to talk about her pet:
&ldquo;Dinah&rsquo;s our cat. And she&rsquo;s such a capital one for catching
mice you can&rsquo;t think! And oh, I wish you could see her after the birds!
Why, she&rsquo;ll eat a little bird as soon as look at it!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00127">
This speech caused a remarkable sensation among the party. Some of the birds
hurried off at once: one old Magpie began wrapping itself up very carefully,
remarking, &ldquo;I really must be getting home; the night-air doesn&rsquo;t
suit my throat!&rdquo; and a Canary called out in a trembling voice to its
children, &ldquo;Come away, my dears! It&rsquo;s high time you were all in
bed!&rdquo; On various pretexts they all moved off, and Alice was soon left
alone.</para>

<para id="en00128">
&ldquo;I wish I hadn&rsquo;t mentioned Dinah!&rdquo; she said to herself in a
melancholy tone. &ldquo;Nobody seems to like her, down here, and I&rsquo;m sure
she&rsquo;s the best cat in the world! Oh, my dear Dinah! I wonder if I shall
ever see you any more!&rdquo; And here poor Alice began to cry again, for she
felt very lonely and low-spirited. In a little while, however, she again heard
a little pattering of footsteps in the distance, and she looked up eagerly,
half hoping that the Mouse had changed his mind, and was coming back to finish
his story.</para>

</chapter>
