<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<chapter id="chapter5-en">

<head2 id="en00200">CHAPTER V.</head2>

<head3 id="en00201">Advice from a Caterpillar</head3>

<para id="en00202">
The Caterpillar and Alice looked at each other for some time in silence: at
last the Caterpillar took the hookah out of its mouth, and addressed her in a
languid, sleepy voice.</para>

<para id="en00203">
&ldquo;Who are &lt;i&gt;you?&lt;/i&gt;&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.
&lt;br/&gt;
This was not an encouraging opening for a conversation. Alice replied, rather
shyly, &ldquo;I&mdash;I hardly know, sir, just at present&mdash;at least I know
who I &lt;i&gt;was&lt;/i&gt; when I got up this morning, but I think I must have been
changed several times since then.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00204">
&ldquo;What do you mean by that?&rdquo; said the Caterpillar sternly.
&ldquo;Explain yourself!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00205">
&ldquo;I can&rsquo;t explain &lt;i&gt;myself&lt;/i&gt;, I&rsquo;m afraid, sir,&rdquo; said
Alice, &ldquo;because I&rsquo;m not myself, you see.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00206">
&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t see,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00207">
&ldquo;I&rsquo;m afraid I can&rsquo;t put it more clearly,&rdquo; Alice replied
very politely, &ldquo;for I can&rsquo;t understand it myself to begin with; and
being so many different sizes in a day is very confusing.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00208">
&ldquo;It isn&rsquo;t,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00209">
&ldquo;Well, perhaps you haven&rsquo;t found it so yet,&rdquo; said Alice;
&ldquo;but when you have to turn into a chrysalis&mdash;you will some day, you
know&mdash;and then after that into a butterfly, I should think you&rsquo;ll
feel it a little queer, won&rsquo;t you?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00210">
&ldquo;Not a bit,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00211">
&ldquo;Well, perhaps your feelings may be different,&rdquo; said Alice;
&ldquo;all I know is, it would feel very queer to &lt;i&gt;me&lt;/i&gt;.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00212">
&ldquo;You!&rdquo; said the Caterpillar contemptuously. &ldquo;Who are
&lt;i&gt;you?&lt;/i&gt;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00213">
Which brought them back again to the beginning of the conversation. Alice felt
a little irritated at the Caterpillar&rsquo;s making such &lt;i&gt;very&lt;/i&gt; short
remarks, and she drew herself up and said, very gravely, &ldquo;I think, you
ought to tell me who &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt; are, first.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00214">
&ldquo;Why?&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00215">
Here was another puzzling question; and as Alice could not think of any good
reason, and as the Caterpillar seemed to be in a &lt;i&gt;very&lt;/i&gt; unpleasant state
of mind, she turned away.</para>

<para id="en00216">
&ldquo;Come back!&rdquo; the Caterpillar called after her. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve
something important to say!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00217">
This sounded promising, certainly: Alice turned and came back again.</para>

<para id="en00218">
&ldquo;Keep your temper,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00219">
&ldquo;Is that all?&rdquo; said Alice, swallowing down her anger as well as she
could.</para>

<para id="en00220">
&ldquo;No,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00221">
Alice thought she might as well wait, as she had nothing else to do, and
perhaps after all it might tell her something worth hearing. For some minutes
it puffed away without speaking, but at last it unfolded its arms, took the
hookah out of its mouth again, and said, &ldquo;So you think you&rsquo;re
changed, do you?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00222">
&ldquo;I&rsquo;m afraid I am, sir,&rdquo; said Alice; &ldquo;I can&rsquo;t
remember things as I used&mdash;and I don&rsquo;t keep the same size for ten
minutes together!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00223">
&ldquo;Can&rsquo;t remember &lt;i&gt;what&lt;/i&gt; things?&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00224">
&ldquo;Well, I&rsquo;ve tried to say &ldquo;How doth the little busy
bee,&rdquo; but it all came different!&rdquo; Alice replied in a very
melancholy voice.</para>

<para id="en00225">
&ldquo;Repeat, &ldquo;&lt;i&gt;You are old, Father William&lt;/i&gt;,&rsquo;&rdquo; said
the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00226">
Alice folded her hands, and began:&mdash;</para>

<para id="en00227">
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;You are old, Father William,&rdquo; the young man said,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;And your hair has become very white;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; And yet you incessantly stand on your head&mdash;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Do you think, at your age, it is right?&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;In my youth,&rdquo; Father William replied to his son,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;I feared it might injure the brain;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; But, now that I&rsquo;m perfectly sure I have none,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Why, I do it again and again.&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;You are old,&rdquo; said the youth, &ldquo;as I mentioned before,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; And have grown most uncommonly fat;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; Yet you turned a back-somersault in at the door&mdash;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Pray, what is the reason of that?&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;In my youth,&rdquo; said the sage, as he shook his grey locks,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;I kept all my limbs very supple&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; By the use of this ointment&mdash;one shilling the box&mdash;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Allow me to sell you a couple?&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;You are old,&rdquo; said the youth, &ldquo;and your jaws are too weak&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; For anything tougher than suet;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; Yet you finished the goose, with the bones and the beak&mdash;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Pray, how did you manage to do it?&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;In my youth,&rdquo; said his father, &ldquo;I took to the law,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; And argued each case with my wife;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; And the muscular strength, which it gave to my jaw,&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Has lasted the rest of my life.&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;You are old,&rdquo; said the youth, &ldquo;one would hardly suppose&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; That your eye was as steady as ever;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; Yet you balanced an eel on the end of your nose&mdash;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; What made you so awfully clever?&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &ldquo;I have answered three questions, and that is enough,&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Said his father; &ldquo;don&rsquo;t give yourself airs!&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; Do you think I can listen all day to such stuff?&lt;br/&gt;
 &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Be off, or I&rsquo;ll kick you down stairs!&rdquo;&lt;br/&gt;
</para>

<para id="en00228">
&ldquo;That is not said right,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00229">
&ldquo;Not &lt;i&gt;quite&lt;/i&gt; right, I&rsquo;m afraid,&rdquo; said Alice, timidly;
&ldquo;some of the words have got altered.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00230">
&ldquo;It is wrong from beginning to end,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar
decidedly, and there was silence for some minutes.</para>

<para id="en00231">
The Caterpillar was the first to speak.</para>

<para id="en00232">
&ldquo;What size do you want to be?&rdquo; it asked.</para>

<para id="en00233">
&ldquo;Oh, I&rsquo;m not particular as to size,&rdquo; Alice hastily replied;
&ldquo;only one doesn&rsquo;t like changing so often, you know.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00234">
&ldquo;I &lt;i&gt;don&rsquo;t&lt;/i&gt; know,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00235">
Alice said nothing: she had never been so much contradicted in her life before,
and she felt that she was losing her temper.</para>

<para id="en00236">
&ldquo;Are you content now?&rdquo; said the Caterpillar.</para>

<para id="en00237">
&ldquo;Well, I should like to be a &lt;i&gt;little&lt;/i&gt; larger, sir, if you
wouldn&rsquo;t mind,&rdquo; said Alice: &ldquo;three inches is such a wretched
height to be.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00238">
&ldquo;It is a very good height indeed!&rdquo; said the Caterpillar angrily,
rearing itself upright as it spoke (it was exactly three inches high).</para>

<para id="en00239">
&ldquo;But I&rsquo;m not used to it!&rdquo; pleaded poor Alice in a piteous
tone. And she thought of herself, &ldquo;I wish the creatures wouldn&rsquo;t be
so easily offended!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00240">
&ldquo;You&rsquo;ll get used to it in time,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar; and it
put the hookah into its mouth and began smoking again.</para>

<para id="en00241">
This time Alice waited patiently until it chose to speak again. In a minute or
two the Caterpillar took the hookah out of its mouth and yawned once or twice,
and shook itself. Then it got down off the mushroom, and crawled away in the
grass, merely remarking as it went, &ldquo;One side will make you grow taller,
and the other side will make you grow shorter.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00242">
&ldquo;One side of &lt;i&gt;what?&lt;/i&gt; The other side of &lt;i&gt;what?&lt;/i&gt;&rdquo; thought
Alice to herself.</para>

<para id="en00243">
&ldquo;Of the mushroom,&rdquo; said the Caterpillar, just as if she had asked
it aloud; and in another moment it was out of sight.</para>

<para id="en00244">
Alice remained looking thoughtfully at the mushroom for a minute, trying to
make out which were the two sides of it; and as it was perfectly round, she
found this a very difficult question. However, at last she stretched her arms
round it as far as they would go, and broke off a bit of the edge with each
hand.</para>

<para id="en00245">
&ldquo;And now which is which?&rdquo; she said to herself, and nibbled a little
of the right-hand bit to try the effect: the next moment she felt a violent
blow underneath her chin: it had struck her foot!</para>

<para id="en00246">
She was a good deal frightened by this very sudden change, but she felt that
there was no time to be lost, as she was shrinking rapidly; so she set to work
at once to eat some of the other bit. Her chin was pressed so closely against
her foot, that there was hardly room to open her mouth; but she did it at last,
and managed to swallow a morsel of the lefthand bit.</para>

<para id="en00247">
&ldquo;Come, my head&rsquo;s free at last!&rdquo; said Alice in a tone of
delight, which changed into alarm in another moment, when she found that her
shoulders were nowhere to be found: all she could see, when she looked down,
was an immense length of neck, which seemed to rise like a stalk out of a sea
of green leaves that lay far below her.</para>

<para id="en00248">
&ldquo;What &lt;i&gt;can&lt;/i&gt; all that green stuff be?&rdquo; said Alice. &ldquo;And
where &lt;i&gt;have&lt;/i&gt; my shoulders got to? And oh, my poor hands, how is it I
can&rsquo;t see you?&rdquo; She was moving them about as she spoke, but no
result seemed to follow, except a little shaking among the distant green
leaves.</para>

<para id="en00249">
As there seemed to be no chance of getting her hands up to her head, she tried
to get her head down to them, and was delighted to find that her neck would
bend about easily in any direction, like a serpent. She had just succeeded in
curving it down into a graceful zigzag, and was going to dive in among the
leaves, which she found to be nothing but the tops of the trees under which she
had been wandering, when a sharp hiss made her draw back in a hurry: a large
pigeon had flown into her face, and was beating her violently with its wings.</para>

<para id="en00250">
&ldquo;Serpent!&rdquo; screamed the Pigeon.</para>

<para id="en00251">
&ldquo;I&rsquo;m &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; a serpent!&rdquo; said Alice indignantly.
&ldquo;Let me alone!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00252">
&ldquo;Serpent, I say again!&rdquo; repeated the Pigeon, but in a more subdued
tone, and added with a kind of sob, &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve tried every way, and
nothing seems to suit them!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00253">
&ldquo;I haven&rsquo;t the least idea what you&rsquo;re talking about,&rdquo;
said Alice.</para>

<para id="en00254">
&ldquo;I&rsquo;ve tried the roots of trees, and I&rsquo;ve tried banks, and
I&rsquo;ve tried hedges,&rdquo; the Pigeon went on, without attending to her;
&ldquo;but those serpents! There&rsquo;s no pleasing them!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00255">
Alice was more and more puzzled, but she thought there was no use in saying
anything more till the Pigeon had finished.</para>

<para id="en00256">
&ldquo;As if it wasn&rsquo;t trouble enough hatching the eggs,&rdquo; said the
Pigeon; &ldquo;but I must be on the look-out for serpents night and day! Why, I
haven&rsquo;t had a wink of sleep these three weeks!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00257">
&ldquo;I&rsquo;m very sorry you&rsquo;ve been annoyed,&rdquo; said Alice, who
was beginning to see its meaning.</para>

<para id="en00258">
&ldquo;And just as I&rsquo;d taken the highest tree in the wood,&rdquo;
continued the Pigeon, raising its voice to a shriek, &ldquo;and just as I was
thinking I should be free of them at last, they must needs come wriggling down
from the sky! Ugh, Serpent!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00259">
&ldquo;But I&rsquo;m &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; a serpent, I tell you!&rdquo; said Alice.
&ldquo;I&rsquo;m a&mdash;I&rsquo;m a&mdash;&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00260">
&ldquo;Well! &lt;i&gt;What&lt;/i&gt; are you?&rdquo; said the Pigeon. &ldquo;I can see
you&rsquo;re trying to invent something!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00261">
&ldquo;I&mdash;I&rsquo;m a little girl,&rdquo; said Alice, rather doubtfully,
as she remembered the number of changes she had gone through that day.</para>

<para id="en00262">
&ldquo;A likely story indeed!&rdquo; said the Pigeon in a tone of the deepest
contempt. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve seen a good many little girls in my time, but never
&lt;i&gt;one&lt;/i&gt; with such a neck as that! No, no! You&rsquo;re a serpent; and
there&rsquo;s no use denying it. I suppose you&rsquo;ll be telling me next that
you never tasted an egg!&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00263">
&ldquo;I &lt;i&gt;have&lt;/i&gt; tasted eggs, certainly,&rdquo; said Alice, who was a very
truthful child; &ldquo;but little girls eat eggs quite as much as serpents do,
you know.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00264">
&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t believe it,&rdquo; said the Pigeon; &ldquo;but if they do,
why then they&rsquo;re a kind of serpent, that&rsquo;s all I can say.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00265">
This was such a new idea to Alice, that she was quite silent for a minute or
two, which gave the Pigeon the opportunity of adding, &ldquo;You&rsquo;re
looking for eggs, I know &lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt; well enough; and what does it matter to me
whether you&rsquo;re a little girl or a serpent?&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00266">
&ldquo;It matters a good deal to &lt;i&gt;me&lt;/i&gt;,&rdquo; said Alice hastily;
&ldquo;but I&rsquo;m not looking for eggs, as it happens; and if I was, I
shouldn&rsquo;t want &lt;i&gt;yours&lt;/i&gt;: I don&rsquo;t like them raw.&rdquo;</para>

<para id="en00267">
&ldquo;Well, be off, then!&rdquo; said the Pigeon in a sulky tone, as it
settled down again into its nest. Alice crouched down among the trees as well
as she could, for her neck kept getting entangled among the branches, and every
now and then she had to stop and untwist it. After a while she remembered that
she still held the pieces of mushroom in her hands, and she set to work very
carefully, nibbling first at one and then at the other, and growing sometimes
taller and sometimes shorter, until she had succeeded in bringing herself down
to her usual height.</para>

<para id="en00268">
It was so long since she had been anything near the right size, that it felt
quite strange at first; but she got used to it in a few minutes, and began
talking to herself, as usual. &ldquo;Come, there&rsquo;s half my plan done now!
How puzzling all these changes are! I&rsquo;m never sure what I&rsquo;m going
to be, from one minute to another! However, I&rsquo;ve got back to my right
size: the next thing is, to get into that beautiful garden&mdash;how &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt;
that to be done, I wonder?&rdquo; As she said this, she came suddenly upon an
open place, with a little house in it about four feet high. &ldquo;Whoever
lives there,&rdquo; thought Alice, &ldquo;it&rsquo;ll never do to come upon
them &lt;i&gt;this&lt;/i&gt; size: why, I should frighten them out of their wits!&rdquo; So
she began nibbling at the righthand bit again, and did not venture to go near
the house till she had brought herself down to nine inches high.</para>

</chapter>
